MAÑAOL, ROBERT JOHN B., CISA, CRISC, CISM, CPA (PH)

Mobile: +1 408-674-1855

Email: manaol2112@gmail.com

Robert John has more than twelve (12) years of meaningful experience in information systems focusing on IT SOX audits, information security audits, business process reviews, internal controls evaluation, compliance audits, and risk management.

During his stay in Deloitte, EY, and Grant Thornton, he gained a very solid experience in managing multiple clients with a highly performing team members in the performance of walkthrough, design and implementation review, and test of operating effectiveness in various industries of international and local clients.

Robert was awarded by ISACA as the 3rd highest scorer among the passers of Certified in Risk and Information Systems Control (CRISC ®) from July - December 2019.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Deloitte

Manager - Risk and Financial Advisory (May 2022 - Present)

RESPONSIBILITIES:

Engagement Management

- Manage multiple groups of highly performing team members in various industries throughout the
 engagement lifecycle from planning, fieldwork and reporting to ensure that high quality deliverables
 are provided, compliant with the Deloitte framework and within set timeline.
- Manage engagement budgets, risks, issues/escalations, and key metrics.
- Responsible in the review and approval of planning documents, workpapers, audit reports.

Business Development

- Manage and build professional relationships with the financial audit team and client's management for both external and internal engagements.
- Identify any new potential business opportunities and introduce/endorse other Deloitte solutions on new and existing clients.

Coaching/Mentoring

 Participate and actively support mentoring/coaching and talent development within the RA practice for succession.

- Conduct continuous on the job training for staff according to project and provide constant feedback and support.
- Set goals, monitor the performance, and provide guidance/direction to drive professional growth.

Ernst and Young

Associate Director/Manager II, Technology Risk (August 2021 – March 2022)

RESPONSIBILITIES:

Engagement Management

- Provide high quality client service, working directly with onshore and/or client teams to understand and evaluate client's IT environment and controls.
- Manage engagements throughout the engagement lifecycle from initiation, planning, execution and reporting to ensure that deliverables are provided as per the expected quality, compliant with the EY methodology and within timelines.
- Manage the engagement risks, issues/escalations and metrics.
- Review the work program, work papers and provide guidance in performing the test procedures.
- Set, coordinate and lead meetings for key engagement milestones and provide periodic status updates to onshore Engagement Management and/or client teams.
- Identify opportunities for improvement/provide recommendations to mitigate the control deficiencies noted.

Business Development

- Develop and maintain team, onshore and client relationships to manage expectations.
- Improve the GDS integration/penetration rate and hours on the current portfolio of accounts.
- Identify any new potential business opportunities on the accounts and introduce/endorse other TR and consulting solutions.

Coaching/Mentoring

- Be the counselor for TR Seniors and/or Consultant and ensure alignment with the counselee's professional/personal goals against the broader team and organization.
- Set goals, monitor the performance, and provide guidance/direction to drive professional growth.
- On the engagements, coach/mentor newer/less experienced engagement team members

GoPro, Inc.

IT Audit Supervisor – IT Internal Audit (June 2016 – August 2021)

RESPONSIBILITIES:

SOX 404 - ITGC, Automated/Application Controls, ELC, SOD, and IPE Testing

- Manage IT audit team/consultants in performing end-to-end audit through planning, review of test
 procedures and results, reporting to senior management of observations, exceptions, and
 recommendations.
- Supervise the performance of walkthroughs and test of controls over logical/physical access security, change management, network security, computer operations, and other IT processes that have financial impact related to significant ERP systems/applications.
- Develop and conduct IT risk assessments, IT security-related projects, and supports various teams to evaluate IT risk and compliance considerations.
- Conduct training and technical guidance to key stakeholders related to logical/physical security, change management, network security, computer operations, and other security related topics.
- Supervise the review of third-party SOC reports and evaluate the impact of control deficiencies identified.
- Pioneered the development of SOD tool that is utilized by GoPro to check for potential conflicts to NetSuite access.

Business Process Review, Data Analytics and Projects (ad hoc projects)

- Conduct walkthrough and perform test of controls effectiveness of business processes which
 include but not limited to Financial Control and Reporting, Order to Cash, Procure to Pay,
 Inventory, Fixed Asset, and Equity
- Perform data analysis using Power BI, MS Excel VBA, and NetSuite Suite Analytics in various business processes to determine process gaps and identify opportunities for improvements.
- Initiate and develop projects that promotes efficiency of manual processes using advanced excel scripts and formulas.

Deloitte Philippines

Senior – Risk Assurance (May 2015 – June 2016)

RESPONSIBILITIES:

- Responsible in the supervision of junior staff in performing the daily work in and out of the clients' premises.
- Perform review of work papers completed by the junior staff.
- Oversees the day-to-day operations of multiple engagements and is involved with regulatory, and accounting issues that arise during the audit engagement.

- Perform IT audit involvement planning, which includes conducting IT survey interviews with client, discussion of IT audit scope with the Assurance Team, budgeting, preparing work plan, and scheduling.
- Provides leadership in the timely delivery of quality services that aim to exceed the expectations of clients.
- Providing ongoing support to the Assurance Team through identification and assessment of risks and related controls
- Supports the Managers in building business client relationships and in leading audit support and special engagements.
- Conducts fieldwork on the more complex areas in scope. This includes formulating recommendations to address control gaps identified. This also involves discussion of the issues and recommendations with the client's management.

IT General Controls Review

Involved in the identification, documentation, assessment, and testing of key IT general controls:

- Performed review of program change management, user access management, and other IT operations for various application systems.
- IT environment reviews for IT governance, IT infrastructure, IT organizational structure and business recovery measures.

Grant Thornton LLP - Philippines

IT Audit Supervisor – Advisory Services (July 2012 – May 2015)

RESPONSIBILITIES:

- Supervise junior staff in the performance of walk through and test of controls over program change management, logical access security and other IT operations affecting significant ERP systems of clients such as Oracle, SAP, QuickBooks, NetSuite
- Review workpapers completed by the junior staff.
- Conduct technical trainings to junior staffs.
- Propose recommendations to clients to address IT control weaknesses and other relevant issues identified.
- Provide ongoing support to the Assurance Team through identification and assessment of IT risks and related controls.
- Conducts fieldwork on the more complex areas in scope. This includes formulating recommendations to address control gaps identified. This also involves discussion of the issues and recommendations with the client's management.

IT General Controls Review

Involved in the identification, documentation, assessment, and testing of key IT general controls:

- Performed test of controls related to logical and physical access controls, user access management, computer operations.
- IT environment reviews for IT governance, IT infrastructure, IT organizational structure and business recovery measures.

Projects and Process Improvement (ad hoc)

- Manage overall process improvement of the Finance Division by developing web applications and windows applications to automate and boost process efficiency using Visual Studio (VB.Net, Macros, SQL)
- Conduct and handle computer applications trainings to Seniors and New Hires (Microsoft Excel, Crystal Reports, and other business-related applications)

PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATIONS

Certified Information Security Manager (CISM), October 2022

Certified in Risk and Information Systems Controls (CRISC), December 2019

Certified Information Systems Auditor (CISA), December 2016

Certified Public Accountant (CPA), Philippines October 2010

EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUND

Tertiary: Polytechnic University of the Philippines - Sta. Mesa, Manila

Bachelor of Science in Accountancy – Major in Accounting (2006-2010)

Secondary: Masantol National High School – Masantol, Pampanga

Awarded as Class Valedictorian (2002-2006)

Sua Elementary School - Masantol, Pampanga

Elementary: Awarded as Class Valedictorian (1996-2002)